A Finding Aid to the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery Records, 1972-2018, bulk 1980-1992, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery records
1972-2018
bulk 1980-1992
Archives of American Art
Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery
AAA.richrich
Archival Resource Key
7.6 Linear feet
The records of Los Angeles art gallery Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery measure 7.6 linear feet and date from 1972 to 2018 with the bulk of the material dating from 1980 to 1992. The collection comprises administrative records, correspondence with colleagues, artists, galleries, and museums, artist files, exhibition files, and printed materials for the Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and other galleries.
Biographical / Historical
The Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery (est. 1980-1993) was a commercial gallery in Los Angeles, California, that focused on conceptual and post-conceptual art.
Richard Kuhlenschmidt (1951- ) studied art and film before becoming an exhibition designer at the Bowers Museum in Santa Ana where he worked with Tom Jancar. The two friends opened and operated the Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery from 1980 until 1982. Kuhlenschmidt continued to operate as the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery from 1982 to 1985, the Kuhlenschmidt Simon Gallery from 1986 to 1988, and again as the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery from 1989 to 1993.
Artists such as Cindy Bernard, Nayland Blake, Barbara Bloom, John Knight, Louise Lawler, William Leavitt, Allan McCollum, Matt Mullican, Jack Pierson, Mitchell Syrop, James Welling, and others were represented by Kuhlenschmidt. The gallery held the exhibition Joe Bishop / AIDS Benefit (1985) and the exhibition Six Projects for Four Cities (1990) highlighting the work of architecture firm Coop Himmelb(l)au.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1979-2014 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1984-1992 (1.0 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Artist's Files, 1972-1996 (4.5 linear feet; Boxes 2-6)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1981-1992 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 6-7)
Series 5: Printed Materials, 1977-2018 (1.0 linear feet; Boxes 7-9)
Scope and Contents
The records of Los Angeles art gallery Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery measure 7.6 linear feet and date from 1972 to 2018 with the bulk of the material dating from 1980 to 1992. The collection comprises administrative records, correspondence with colleagues, artists, galleries, and museums, artist files, exhibition files, and printed materials for the Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and other galleries.
Administrative records consist of address and appointment books, guest books, gallery history records, and business records. Artist files are for Cindy Bernard, Nayland Blake, Barbara Bloom, John Knight, Louise Lawler, William Leavitt, Allan McCollum, Matt Mullican, Jack Pierson, Mitchell Syrop, James Welling, and others.
Exhibition files include records of the final exhibition held at the Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery in 1982, the Coop Himmelb(l)au exhibition Six Projects for Four Cities (1990), the symposium "Welcome to the Millenium: Architecture Strikes Back," and a few other exhibitions. Printed materials are for the Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and other galleries.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery records were donated in 2001 and 2014 by Richard Kuhlenschmidt.
Related Materials
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an interview with Richard Kuhlenschmidt conducted on June 27, 2014 by Hunter Drohojowska-Philp, for the Archives of American Art, at the Jonathan Club in Santa Monica, C.A. and the Jancar Gallery records, circa 1972-2015, bulk 2006-2015.
Conceptual art; Art galleries, Commercial -- California; Sound recordings; Kuhlenschmidt, Richard; Bloom, Barbara, 1951-; Mullican, Matt, 1951-; McCollum, Allan, 1944-; Lawler, Louise
- Administrative Records, 1979-2014; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains an address book; three appointment books; two guestbooks; documents regarding the Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, as well as a project space in Las Vegas; price lists; agreements for loans to artwork to the Whitney Museum of American Art, Museum of Modern Art, "The Köln Show," and the exhibition Art Against AIDS; and a few other administrative files.
  - Address Book, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Photocopy
  - Appointment Book, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Books, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    2 books
  - Artists Rejected by Gallery, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Employment Applications, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Loans, Outgoing, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gallery History, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gallery, Project Space in Las Vegas, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gallery Publicity, 1984-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gallery Tax Audit, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Guestbook, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Guestbook, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, 1979-circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kuhlenschmidt Resume, 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mailing Lists, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Price Lists, Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Price Lists, Other Galleries, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Purchase Order for "Los Angeles 1970-1975" Art Catalogs, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, circa 1984-1992; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence is with artists, business colleagues, galleries, and museums in Europe and the United States discussing exhibitions, loans, sales, and other topics related to the gallery.
  - A, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Achenbach, Helge, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Air de Paris, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Aruna, Olivia, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - B, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Burgin, Christine, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - C, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - D, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - de Carlo, Massimo, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Diehl, Volker, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Enterprise en Art, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Erwin, John, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - European Correspondents, Incoming, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - European Correspondents, Outgoing, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - European Correspondents, Outgoing, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - F, 1989-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - G, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grunert, Tanja, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gruppo in Paradigma, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - H, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hendler, Jeannette, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hufkens, Xavier, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - I, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - J, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - K, 1988-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Krinzinger, Ursula, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kubinski, Achim, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - L, 1987-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - M, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - N, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - P, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pailhas, Roger, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pakesch, Peter, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Petropoulos, Petros, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Postcards, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - R, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - S, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Serpentine Gallery, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Skarstedt, Per, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Spellman, Lisa (303 Gallery), 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sprüth, Monika, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - T, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - U, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - V, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - W, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Wernicke, Ralph, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Westreich, Thea, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Yamana, Yasuo (Seibu Art Gallery), 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Zucker, S., 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Artist's Files, 1972-1996; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 4.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-6
  Files on artists include slides and photographs of artwork, clippings, paste-ups for gallery promotions, resumes, price lists, exhibition plans and budgets, correspondence, and printed materials on Cindy Bernard, Nayland Blake, Barbara Bloom, John Knight, Louise Lawler, William Leavitt, Allan McCollum, Matt Mullican, Jack Pierson, Mitchell Syrop, James Welling, and others.
  - Artists, B-K, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Artists, K-S, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Artists, T, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Adams, Dennis, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Amico, David, 1972-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Armaly, Fareed, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Asher, Michael, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Askevold, David, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Bart, Cecil, 1987-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Bernard, Cindy, 1987-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44-46)
  - Blake, Nayland, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Blake, Nayland, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Bloom, Barbara, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
  - Brane, Jerry, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Brauntuch, Troy, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cabrera, David, 1989-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cazal, Phillipe, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Currin, John, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Diamond, Jessica, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Drohojowska, Hunter, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Duff, Dana, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ebner, Tim, 1982-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ericson, Kate and Mel Ziegler, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Espaliu, Pepe, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Evans, Steven, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Faust, Gretchen, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Fend, Peter, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Ganahl, Rainer, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Gerber, Gaylen, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Grünfeld, Thomas, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hajamadi, Fariba, 1987-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hashimoto, Kelly, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hopkins, Peter, 1986-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hubbard, Kim, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Huebler, Douglas, circa 1984-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Johnson, Larry, 1984-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kilimnik, Karen, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Knight, John, 1981-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Larner, Liz, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lawler, Louise, 1978-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Leavitt, William, 1983-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16-18)
  - Leccia, Ange, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Leckman, Lori, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Loch, Anne, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Locher, Thomas, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - McCollum, Allan, 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - McCollum, Allan, 1982-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  - Mullican, Matt, 1980-1992; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Folder 7-18)
  - Nagy, Peter, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Oppenheim, Erik, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Pierson, Jack, 1990-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Pierson, Jack, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Reynolds, Jane, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rivkin, Lena, circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Schuster, Michael, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Staehle, Wolfgang, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stewart, Cynthia, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Stingel, Rudolf, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Syrop, Mitchell, 1981-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Thomas, Morgan, circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Thomas, Phillipe, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tzanetopoulos, Paul, 1980-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Walsh, Anne, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Welling, James, 1983-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
  - Winters, Robin, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Wurm, Erwin, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Zobernig, Heimo, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Various Artists, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Exhibition Files, 1981-1992; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  The series contains price and artwork lists, correspondence, printed materials, artist biographical information, loan agreements, and other material documenting the final exhibition at the Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, the Joe Bishop / AIDS Benefit (1985), Sculpture from Werkstatt Kollerschlag (1990), and a few other exhibitions. The files for Coop Himmelb(l)au contain material on the exhibition Six Projects for Four Cities (1990) held at the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and the coinciding symposium "Welcome to the Millenium: Architecture Strikes Back."
  - Thrift Store Paintings (1981), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Group Show," Final Exhibition at Jancar Kuhlenschmidt Gallery (1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Joe Bishop / AIDS Benefit (1985), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Common Market (1990), 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Coop Himmelb(l)au Exhibition and Symposium, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 25-27)
    Includes material for the exhibition Six Projects for Four Cities (1990) and symposium "Welcome to the Millenium: Architecture Strikes Back."
  - Marcel Mariën Exhibition at Galería La Máquina Española (1990), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Sculpture from Werkstatt Kollerschlag (1990), 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - A Summer Drawing Show (1992), 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
- Printed Materials, 1977-2018; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 7-9
  The series consists of artwork reproductions of a "garden" series, brochures and booklets, clippings relating to the gallery and artists represented, exhibition announcements and catalogs for the Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery and other galleries, posters, magazines and journals, and gallery press releases.
  - Artwork Reproductions of "Garden" Series, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Brochures and Booklets, 1984-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Business Cards for Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Richard Kuhlenschmidt Gallery, 1980-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14-16)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Other Galleries, 1977-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17-21)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Other Galleries, 1984-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  - Exhibition Posters, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Magazines and Journals, 1981-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Magazines and Journals, 1984-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Press Releases, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)